Guide to the Anne T. Lawrence Mine Workers Oral History collection, 1972-1973 LAC0006
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Anne T. Lawrence Mine Workers Oral History Collection
1972 March - 1973 January
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
LAC0006
2.5 Linear Feet 1 Document Box, 2 Boxes containing 60 Audio Cassettes, 1 Bound Volume
This collection contains the oral history cassette tapes from Anne T. Lawrence's Mine Workers Oral History Project.
Scope and Contents
The Anne T. Lawrence Mine Workers Oral History Collection was a "Youthgrant" project from the National Endowment for the Humanities to the Miner's Voice, an independent newspaper for rank and file miners published in Charleston, WV. This collection contains the audio cassette oral histories carried out by Anne Lawrence, transcriptions, and the bound and printed final report.
Biographical / Historical
In the 1920s-1930s, the central Appalachian coal fields were the scene of heavy industrial warfare. The coal operators believed that maintaining the open shop while under pricing their competitors would preserve their share of a dwindling market. The United Mine Workers (U.M.W.A.) needed to solidify the coal fields or face potential losses of previously unionized mines and operators. After World War I, union membership was at an all time high but the companies began implementing open shop techniques: labor injunctions, "yellow-dog" contracts, company spies, imported strikebreakers, company unions, and bribing local authorities. The union had always been strong in the hard coal fields in eastern Pennsylvania and the "Central Competitive" soft coal fields of Illinois, Ohio, Indiana, and western Pennsylvania. Due to lack of rail facilities and infrastructure, the southern fields of West Virginia, Virginia, Kentucky, and Tennessee, were late to develop and the union did not have a historical presence. As the demand for coal leveled off, the industry became plagued with chronic overproduction. Wages not protected by the union fell with the price of coal. In that economic market, the operators paying non-union wages maintained a competitive advantage over the union mines.
As more of the union mines were either bankrupting or repudiating their contracts, the U.M.W.A. decided that consolidating the Appalachian coal fields was of primary concern. Coal operators in that region, backed by private detective organizations, such as the Baldwin-Felts Agency, intimidated union organizers, blacklisted, fired, or physically assaulted miners, and maintained a strict control of the working conditions. In addition, operators typically paid the salaries of local sheriff offices, typically in the tonnage rate. With travel difficult, miners were very isolated from other mines and other labor movements.
Violence between the coal operators and miners during that time was extreme. Countless union organizers and sympathetic miners were murdered and beaten and eventually retaliated. The Matewan Massacre in Mingo County, West Virginia; the Battle of Blair Mountain in Logan County West Virginia; and the Battle of Evarts in Harlan County, West Virginia are all examples of this working class violence. The skirmishes mostly ended with the National Industrial Recovery Act of 1933 and the efforts of then U.M.W.A. president John L. Lewis.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into 1 series: Oral History Audio Cassettes.
General
West Virginia Mine Wars, W. Va., 1897-1921; Labor disputes--West Virginia; Blair Mountain, Battle of, W. Va., 1921
- Oral History Audio Cassettes, 1972 March 5-October 3; Series 1
  Scope and Contents
  The Oral History Audio Cassettes include topics of mine operations during a period of heavy labor unrest. Topics include "Yellow-dog" contracts, blacklisting, wage gouging, strikes, corruption, and protests. There are discussions of union organizing with the United Mine Workers of America, the American Federation of Labor, the Congress of Industrial Organizations and the effects of the National Industrial Recovery Act of 1933 and the efforst of John L. Lewis. There are discussions of violence from the local sheriffs, strike busters, private detectives such as the Baldwin-Felts Agency, coal miners and coal operators. Counties discussed are Harlan and Letcher Counties in Kentucky, and Logan, Boone, McDowell, and Mingo Counties in West Virginia.
  Arrangement
  Series is arranged alphabetically by last name.
  - Henry Clay Pettry Interview, 1972 September 13 (Box 2, Cassette 44, Cassette 43)
    General
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 13 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Henry Clay Pettry lived in Lawson, West Virginia. Brother of Bill Pettry, U.M.W.A. District 17 Vice President, who shot Logan County Sheriff Don Chafin in 1919. Mr. Pettry discussed the lead up to and the events after the March on Logan and the Battle of Blair Mountain, living conditions in mining towns, and the efforts to organize union activity.
  - John Wilburn Interview, 1972 September 2 (Box 2, Cassette 56)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 19 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    John Wilburn lived in Julian, West Virginia. He was convicted in Charles Town, West Virginia, along with Bill Blizzard, and several other union organizers, of murdering Deputy Sheriff John Gore during the Battle of Blair Mountain. Mr. Wilburn discussed the entire situation from the beginning, including the Matewan Massacre involving Sid Hatfield, the Baldwin-Felts Agency, and Ed Chambers, and the resulting violence in Logan County.
  - Grace Jackson Interview, 1972 July 25 (Box 2, Cassette 33)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 23 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Grace Jackson lived in Eskdale, West Virginia. A very self sufficient woman, Ms. Jackson participated in all union organization in Logan County. She discussed the highly prosperous days of the coal operators, and what economic opportunities were available to the women at that time. She talked of the Battle of Blair Mountain from a supporter's standpoint.
    Link to transcript
    A transcript of the audio file may be found here: https://archive.org/details/LAC0006_s1_PooleHoward_transcript
    https://archive.org/details/LAC0006_s1_PooleHoward_transcript
  - Lena Blizzard Harlow Interview, 1972 August 9 (Box 1, Cassette 25)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 31 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Lena Blizzard Harlow lived in Ohley, West Virginia. Sister of Bill Blizzard, organizer of the Battle of Blair Mountain. She discussed her family's involvement and the point of view that union organization did not take hold due to the miner's selling out.
  - Frank Blizzard Interview, circa 1972 (Box 1, Cassette 2)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 34 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Frank Blizzard lived in Ohley, West Virginia. He was the youngest brother of Bill Blizzard. He was too young to participate, but retold the story of the Battle of Blair Mountain.
  - Mary Payne Interview, 1972 August 9 (Box 1, Cassette 30)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 37 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Mary Payne lived in Eskdale, West Virinia. Her husband and brother in law were involved in the Battle of Blair Mountain. Ms. Payne felt her place was in the home and did not get involved.
  - Camden McDornan Interview, 1972 October 3 (Box 2, Cassette 40, Cassette 39)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 39 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Camden McDornan lived in Brushton, West Virginia. He worked in Boone County in union mine territory but was part of the Battle of Blair Mountain. He discussed the organization of the battle and the resulting surrender to the National Guard.
  - Willie Epps Interview, circa 1972 (Box 1, Cassette 15)
    Interview was conducted by Bob Hauptman and the report can be found on page 39 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Willie Epps lived in Fireco, West Virginia. He discussed living conditions in mining towns as a black man. He recalled the hardships of all miners, regardless of race, and the change in technology over the years. He worked in union mines and received his pension and is a strong union man.
    A transcript of the audio file may be found here: https://archive.org/details/LAC0006_S1_Epps_transcript
    https://archive.org/details/LAC0006_S1_Epps_transcript
  - Agnew Thomas Interview, 1972 October 3 (Box 2, Cassette 52)
    Interview was conducted by Bob Hauptman and the report can be found on page 45 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Agnew Thomas lived in Sylvester, West Virginia. He is married to Artie Thomas. When Agnew was 18, he joined in the Battle of Blair Mountain. He discussed the controversy surrounding the ending of the battle, and expressed a feeling that everyone has sold out. He was secretary of his local when he retired from a mine in Boone County.
  - Artie Thomas Interview, circa 1972 (Box 2, Cassette 53)
    Interview was conducted by Bob Hauptman and the report can be found on page 48 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Artie Thomas lived in Sylvester, West Virginia. She is the wife of Agnew Thomas. She adds to Mr. Thomas's stories during the interview.
  - Brice Hunter Interview, 1972 September 14 (Box 1, Cassette 26)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 49 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Brice Hunter lived in Racine, West Virginia. Mr. Hunter discussed the killing of Deputy Sheriff John Gore. As an outsider working in the nearby glass plant, he recalled the plight of his working brethren.
  - Elbert Gore Interview, 1972 August 8 (Box 1, Cassette 22)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 53 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Elbert Gore lived in Holden, WV. His father was deputy sheriff John Gore, who was shot by a group of miners during the Battle of Blair Mountain. Mr. Gore was a school teacher and was not involved with the law, but was taken hostage by miners regardless. He discussed the Battle of Blair Mountain, including the many times he felt his life was in danger. He eventually became a sheriff in spite of his previous experiences.
  - Dewey Browning Interview, 1972 July 3 (Box 1, Cassette 6)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 61 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Dewey Browning lived in Switzer, West Virginia. Mr. Browning discussed the life of a union miner that played both sides. He had worked for Sheriff Don Chafin in the past which gave him the ability to avoid violence. He discussed the Battle of Blair Mountain as a nonparticipant and the aftermath of union organization.
  - Mrs. Howard Young Interview, 1972 September 15 (Box 2, Cassette 60)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 66 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Mrs. Howard Young lived in Holden, West Virginia. She was pregnant and giving birth during the Battle of Blair Mountain. Her husband Howard Young was involved in the march.
  - Josh Chafin Interview, 1972 September 20 (Box 1, Cassette 8)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 68 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Josh Chafin lived in Cora, West Virginia. Mr. Chafin worked in mines but was forced to join the sides of the coal operators and the deputies. He stated that he did not want to fight, or get fired, so he went up to the Battle of Blair Mountain and did not participate. A veteran of World War I, he realized what he needed to do to stay alive.
  - George T. Swain Interview, 1972 September 1 (Box 2, Cassette 51, Cassette 50)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 71 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    George Swain lived in Charleston, West Virginia. A retired miner that sided with Sheriff Don Chafin, Mr. Swain became a reporter for the Logan Banner. He discussed in great detail the Battle of Blair Mountain. He also discussed living conditions and the power of the coal operators.
  - William D. Gothard Interview, 1972 September 16 (Box 1, Cassette 23)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 82 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    William Gothard lived in Cora, West Virginia. Mr. Gothard worked in the Logan County mines for over 50 years. He claimed to be a neutral and used his ability as a bootlegger to remain so. He discussed his interactions with his fellow miners and Sheriff Don Chafin.
  - Charles Literal Interview, 1972 July 10 (Box 2, Cassette 45, Cassette Side A, Cassette 37, Cassette Side B)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 87 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Charles Literal lived in Logan, West Virginia. A retired miner, Mr. Literal was known as the local history buff. He retold the story of the Matewan Massacre and the Battle of Blair Mountain.
  - Pinhead Jones Interview, 1972 July 10 (Box 2, Cassette 45, Cassette Side B)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 91 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Pinhead Jones lived in Logan, West Virginia. Mr. Jones moved from Alabama and worked for the Island Creek Coal Company for nearly 40 years. He stated that Sheriff Don Chafin offered to pay him to fight against the miners, but refused and hid out throughout the Battle of Blair Mountain. He gave President Roosevelt all the credit for the miners' right to organize.
  - Spencer D. Brinegar Interview, 1972 March 5 (Box 1, Cassette 4)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 93 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
  - Mary Ghiz Interview, 1972 (Box 1, Cassette 19, Cassette Side A)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 96 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Mary Ghiz lived in Logan, West Virginia. Her father, John Ghiz, immigrated to the United States in 1904 from Hungary. Her father was peddling clothes and eventually became Logan's first confectioner. Ms. Ghiz recalled the time of the Battle of Blair Mountain from a neutral viewpoint.
  - Georgie McCloud Interview, 1972 August 16 (Box 1, Cassette 28, Cassette Side B)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 98 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Georgie McCloud lived in Harts, WV. She wrote down her thoughts (included in the report) and most of the interview consists of her discussing her family's involvement in the Battle of Blair Mountain. Ms. McCloud's brother Wayne sided with the miners and her brother Gordon side with the coal operators and served as personal bodyguard to Sheriff Don Chafin.
  - Ira P. Hager Interview, 1972 September 8 (Box 1, Cassette 24)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 100 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Ira Hager lived in Meadowbrook Hills, West Virginia. Mr. Hager was a lawyer in Logan and handled murder cases in addition to preparing affidavits that detailed the violation of miners civil rights. He was part of a Republican coalition organized to break the strength of the coal industry Democratic dominated regime in the county.
    A transcript of the audio file may be found here: https://archive.org/details/LAC0006_S1_Hager_transcript
    https://archive.org/details/LAC0006_S1_Hager_transcript
  - Harry Dingess Interview, 1972 September 6 (Box 1, Cassette 13)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 103 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Harry Dingess lived in Barnabus, West Virginia. He was a Sheriff under Don Chafin, but too young to participate in the Battle of Blair Mountain. Mr. Dingess then went on to work in the coal mines and discussed his life since.
  - Richard Burgett Interview, 1972 September 15 (Box 1, Cassette 7)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 105 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Richard Burgett lived in Monaville, West Virginia. He worked in the mines in Mingo County and was threatened with a yellow dog contract. Although the miners in Mingo would heavily involved in striking and union organizing, they could not participate in the Battle of Blair Mountain as they would have had to pass through Logan and the route was blocked by private detectives. Mr. Burgett moved to Logan County in the 1920s and joined the union when the U.M.W.A. finally gained ground after the passage of the National Industrial Recovery Act of 1933.
    A transcript of the audio file may be found here: https://archive.org/details/LAC0006_S1_Burgett_transcript
    https://archive.org/details/LAC0006_S1_Burgett_transcript
  - Bea Curtis Interview, circa 1972 (Box 1, Cassette 10, Cassette 11)
    Interview was conducted by Bob Hauptman and the report can be found on page 117 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Bea Curtis lived in Williamson, West Virginia. Her father and husband both worked in the mines. Ms. Curtis was involved, along with a portion of the black miners, with the Matewan Massacre by assisting in guerilla like activity in Wise County Virginia. She discussed living conditions with government assistance.
  - James Washington Interview, circa 1972 (Box 1, Cassette 3, Box 2, Cassette 54)
    Interview was conducted by Bob Hauptman and the report can be found on page 119 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    James Washington lived in Williamson, West Virginia. He was too young to remember any violence and did not start mining until after unions were established. Mr. Washington was a District Director for the Mingo County Economic Opportunity Council, and discusses living conditions in the area.
  - Louis Bradford Interview, circa 1972 (Box 1, Cassette 3)
    Interview was conducted by Bob Hauptman and the report can be found on page 121 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Louis Bradford lived in Williamson, West Virginia. He outlined details from the Blair Mountain struggle as well as living conditions in the mines. He was present during James Washington's interview and quickly interrupted with stories.
  - Bascombe Hyatt Interview, circa 1972 (Box 1, Cassette 27)
    Interview was conducted by an unidentified interviewer and the report can be found on page 123 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Bascombe Hyatt lived in Williamson, West Virginia. Mr. Hyatt worked in all sorts of mines, both union and nonunion, and earned a reputation as a scab. He claimed that a man has to provide for his family and does not see the need for unions if the men get paid regardless.
  - Luther Keen Interview, 1972 September 21 (Box 2, Cassette 35)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 125 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Luther Keen lived in Holden, West Virginia. Mr. Keen worked in the mines for over 40 years and was president of the first local union, #5813, at the Holden #7 mine. He discussed living conditions before the union and the opportunities the union provided after it was established.
  - Edward Perry Interview, 1972 September 16 (Box 2, Cassette 42)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 128 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Edward Perry lived in Holden, West Virginia. Mr. Perry discussed living conditions in the mines under the Island Creek Coal Company and the #22 Holden mine explosion. He gave his perspective on the organization of unions and the scabs/union busters that came into town creating violent times. He also discussed the Battle of Blair Mountain, Matewan Massacre, and March on Logan incidents.
  - Sid Conley Interview, 1972 September 20 (Box 1, Cassette 9)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 133 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Sid Conley lived in Mud Fork, West Virginia. He worked for the Island Creek Coal Company and discussed the union organization struggles. He attributed the lack of organization to the authorities and their unrightfully persecution. Mr. Conley was a proud supporter of unions.
    A transcript of the audio file may be found here: https://archive.org/details/LAC0006_S1_Conley_Transcript/mode/2up
    https://archive.org/details/LAC0006_S1_Conley_Transcript/mode/2up
  - Mandy "Grandma" Porter Interview, 1972 September 27 (Box 2, Cassette 46)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 135 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Mandy "Grandma" Porter lived in Verdunville, West Virginia. She discussed the living conditions in McDowell and Mingo Counties and the organization of union activity. She moved to Logan County in 1923 and says it was much worse until the National Industrial Recovery Act of 1933.
  - Mrs. L. Dow Browning Interview, 1972 September 27 (Box 2, Cassette 55, Cassette Side B)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 143 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Mrs. L. Dow Browning lived in Verduneville, West Virginia. She discussed conditions during the early years of the union, specifically on the Gay Coal Company – where her husband worked for over 60 years. The mine was not a union mine and the coal operators were against it, but she recollected that both the miners and the operators respected each other.
  - Otis Kinser Interview, circa 1972 (Box 1, Cassette 19, Cassette Side B)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 145 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Otis Kinser lived in Logan, West Virginia. Mr. Kinser discussed the living conditions in Logan and the fear of the authorities and the force they used to deter union activity.
  - Lee Johnson Interview, 1972 September 28 (Box 2, Cassette 34)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 147 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Lee Johnson lived in Monaville, West Virginia. Mr. Johnson discussed life in the mines of Logan County without a union, and how most miners did not have knowledge of organized labor. He talked about Sheriff Don Chafin and detailed the use of "shadow unions" until the National Industrial Recovery Act of 1933. He stated that thousands turned out for the first organizing meeting in Logan.
  - Elijah Mays Interview, 1972 September 16 (Box 2, Cassette 38)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 151 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Elijah Mays lived in Holden, West Virginia. After starting out in the lumber business, Mr. Mays spent the majority of his life working in the mines of Logan County. A lifelong union man, he did not participate in the Battle at Blair Mountain as he would not raise arms against a fellow union miner. He suspects that most men were union men at heart, but the overbearing presence of Sheriff Don Chafin's deputies and the fear of arrest kept most men silent.
  - Frank Deen Interview, 1972 September 21 (Box 1, Cassette 12)
    Interview was conducted by Anne T. Lawrence and the report can be found on page 154 of "On Dark and Bloody Ground".
    Frank Deen lived in Holden, West Virginia. After emigrating from Italy, Mr. Deen spent the majority of his life working the mines of the Island Creek Coal Company. A supporter of unions, he discussed living conditions and working conditions in the mines during the Depression, as well as life as an immigrant.